Guide to the Romance language collection, 1678-1923
Department of Special Collections
Romance language collection,
1678-1923
Special Collections M0128
1.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Various sources
SCOPE AND CONTENT
Several small collections of letters, civil documents, literary mss. in Spanish, Catalan, Italian and Latin and two translations from Spanish to English.
CONTAINER LIST
- SPANISH
  - CARIEDO Y PEREDO, [FRANCISCO]. (Box 1, Volume 1)
    - Libro de la Obra Agua. Fundada en las Casas de Aiuntamiento (Ayuntamiento) por el Gral. Don Franz.co Cariedo y Peredo. El Dia 4 de Abril en el Año de 1748.Manila, Philippines - water rights. Actual record of ms. begins in 1764.Book was to replace records lost in a British raid in 1762.Inclusive to 1838.Contains a number of signatures of various officials.
  - DEFINICIONES DE FISICA PARTICULAR Y GENERAL. (Box 1, Volume 2)
    - Notebook on various subjects (science, logic, psychology, theology, metaphysics, etc.) by various hands. Several names appear: Fray Julian [Adan], Fray Pedro de la V. de la Paz (1853 and 54),Fray [Gondioso] de la V. del Agua (1852).
  - ECHEVERRIA Y VEYTIA, MARIANO JOSÉ FERNANDEZ DE (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Typescript English translation of his travels 1737-1740from Mexico to Cuba to Spain and in Spain and France. Translator unknown, location of originals unknown.
  - GONZALEZ Y MONTOYA, DON JOSÉ (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1. Hoja de servicios de Don José Gonzalez y Montoya, caballero del ordende Santiago, y honorario del Conejo de Hacienda: obtiene 50 [], medis suelds, como cesante de la Superintendencia y Direccion General de Fabios en la Habana; [si?] edad 64 annos [] estado casado []; Ms. record of his services 1767-1823. 2. Relacion de Meritos y Servicios 1801-06.Peru.
  - KALONGE, FR. ANTONIO and [Fr. Joaquin del Rosario]. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Campo Evangelico en Tagalo Planteo Tercero para el Tiempo de Resurreccion hasta Aviento. Bound volume, no covers, n.d.,n.p.
  - LUNA Y DRUSINA, FERNANDO (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Perjura!... Ptd. poem with ms. additions.
  - MADERO, FRANCISCO INDALECIO. 1873-1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1912, Jul. 18.T.L.S. to Philos Cooke.
  - [MENDEZ, CAPT. G.] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Algo sobre el arte antiguo de los Indios en el Salvador 1884.
  - VALLE, RAFAEL HELIDORO (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ca. 25 poems. Typescript and printed, some with ms. corrections., Typescript of speech.
  - VILLA, FRANCISCO (PANCHO). (Real name: Doreto Arango), 1877-1923. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1. 1914, Jul. 30.T.L.S. Aguirre Penavide, L.(sec.) to Philos Cooke.
    - 2. 1914, Aug. 13.T.L.S. Perez Rul, Enrique (aide) to Philos Cooke.
    - 3. 1915, Mar. 26.T.L.S. [Villa, Francisco] to Philos Cooke.
  - REVILLA GIGEDO, JUAN VICENTE GÜÉMEZ PACHECO DE PADILLA HORCASITAS, CONDE DE. 1740-1799. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Instruccion del Estado de Esta America que Entregó Altypo del su Partida el Exmo. Sr. Marques de Branciforte. Año de 1794.Account of Mexican viceroy's administration 1789-1794.Governing Indians, status of courts, taxes, customs, explorations, reforms, recommendations to successor. Goleta, Alessandro Malaspina, Nootka, Monterey, San Diego, San Francisco, canal of Santa Barbara, José de Bustamante, etc.
  - ZAVALA, LORENZO DE (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Viage a los Estados-Unidos del Norte de America. Paris, Imprenta de Decourchant, Calle d' Erfurth, No. 1, Junto a la Abadia 1834.
      - 1. Pencil list of original sources in English.
      - 2. Typed translation and prologue with ms. corrections.
  - GAINZA, DON JOSEF DE & GAINZA, DON MANUEL JOSEF DE. (Box 2, Folder 12a)
    - Detailed record of legal proceedings begun and carried out by Don Josef to establish his son's proviledges to nobility. 1783, March -proceedings begun, ending favorably for Don Josef in 1785.
- CATALAN
  - MEDITA POUR LA RETRE (binders title)., 2 bound vols. (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - Recopilacio de algunos meditations, Losquals poden entredia [servir?] de leceura proporcionada a qui fa los exercisis spirituals de St. Ignac[io] [de Loyola?]...
- ITALIAN
  - RONCONI, SEBASTIAN (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - [1871]A.L.S. to Sig. Pollini.
  - MONTI, VICINO, 1754-1828 (Box 2, Folder 16a)
    - A handwritten play. "A Pittagonci, Azione Dramatica di Giuseppe Napolenone"
  - Pulaseagri[g?] (Box 2, Folder 16b)
    - A.L.S. to Carrisima Ipetrino, 1907 Mar. 22 & 26
  - SARTY, CESARE (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1873.A.L.S. to Signor Verger.
- LATIN
  - Latin Facsimile (Box 3, Folder 18)
Detailed record of legal proceedings begun and carried out by Don Josef de Gainza on behalf of son, Don Manuel Josef de Gainza, for purpose of establishing son's rights to privileges of nobility. Record of proceedings, involving tracing of son's genealogy, reported step by step, with names of witnesses and officials concerned included. Proceedings begun in March, 1783, and concluded favorably for Don Josef de Gainza in 1785. At end of record of proceedings appear certificates signed by officials in Valladolid, Spain, in June, 1784, by officials in village of Deva, Mexico (Province of Guipúzcoa), in December, 1784, and by King of Spain at Aranjuez, Spain, in May, 1785.